A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, Projects, International Relations, RG 1.3, Series 155 FA388A
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, Projects, International Relations, RG 1.3, Series 155
1971-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA388A
63 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Projects include:
FA386 Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.1
FA387 Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.2
FA388 Rockefeller Foundation records, projects, RG 1.3
Biographical / Historical
In December 1972, a program committee of Trustees of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) was appointed to conduct a formal review of the overall programs and policies of the RF since 1958. One result of this review was the establishment in 1973 of a new program titled Conflict in International Relations (CIR), under the guidance of Elmore Jackson and Joseph E. Black, Director for Social Sciences. The program, under the Division of Social Sciences, was to be "directed toward the support of measures for the anticipation, avoidance, and resolution of conflicts that are likely to disrupt the international community, and the development of international institutions with greater capacity for dealing effectively with emerging issues of global interdependency." (RF Annual Report, 1973, p. 10)
During its first 18 months, emphasis was placed on analyzing several of the basic emerging issues in the international community – including the economic and security implications of scarce resources, the impact of population growth, low food reserves, possible climate change, and the escalation of military budgets in response to the increased costs of ever more sophisticated military equipment (E. Jackson to J. Leonard, January 24, 1975) – and in holding discussions with research and foundation executives in the United States and overseas. Building on this analysis and these discussions, the CIR program in 1975 began to devote more attention both to the means through which international institutions capable of handling these issues could be developed and to the development of leadership through its fellowships.
In its early years, CIR's areas of focus included: International economic and resource issues; arms control and international security; new approaches to world order; and analysis of particular conflicts. The emphasis was on the anticipation, control, and resolution of conflict. Grants were given to institutions, awards made to outstanding persons in the field of international relations, and conferences were sponsored.
In 1976, the RF Trustees authorized a new Division of International Relations with Mason Willrich as its Director, and in 1977, following a major review of the CIR program, a revised program – titled International Relations (IR) – was approved and launched under the Division of International Relations.
The new IR program was to focus on three areas: World energy; world food and agriculture; and regional conflicts and security arrangements. Further adjustments to the program were made in 1978, with areas of focus defined as: World energy; international economic policy; and regional conflicts and security arrangements.
Within each of these areas, the primary objectives were: "(1) to identify core problems for which cooperative action is or will be required for effective management, or for the avoidance or resolution of major conflict; (2) to assess such problems from a global perspective and in context in order to develop and evaluate alternative courses of action for coping with them; (3) to encourage development of scholarly and professional competence in policy analysis; and (4) to increase public understanding of the issues and alternatives and the need for timely action." (RF Annual Report, 1979, p. 81)
Through its IR program, RF supported efforts "to promote international collaboration in pursuit of long-term common national interests; that stress the need for practical solutions that can command wide public support rather than theoretical grand designs; that bring a variety of disciplines to bear on issues; and that address problems in a multidisciplinary fashion." (RF Annual Report, 1980, p. 66)
In December 1981, the RF revised its guidelines for the IR program. The component on world energy problems was phased out. The program, beginning in 1982, would make grants that supported independent research and policy analysis of the long-range interests that governments have in international security and economic cooperation. Aware that peaceful relations among nations was a vital corollary to the objectives of its grantmaking efforts, the RF set the following goals for the IR program, as outlined in the Foundation's 1982 Annual Report (p. 65):
1. Within the United States, to strengthen the contribution of nongovernmental international relations research to U. S. foreign policy
2. In countries other than the United States, to strengthen the analytical capacity of international relations research institutions that can operate substantially without government constraint and have the potential to increase the intellectual underpinnings of these countries' foreign policies
3. To provide more effective opportunities for public and private experts from different countries to analyze problems jointly and develop practical solutions that can command wide public support
4. Through its fellowship program and other mechanisms, to identify outstanding young people trained in international relations and increase their opportunities for career development.
Over the next few years, the IR program continued its emphasis on international security and economic cooperation, providing funding to strengthen the contribution of independent research and policy analysis to the articulation of the long-range interests facing governments in these areas. In 1983, the Foundation made several experimental grants to encourage American women leaders to engage in the debate over U. S. national security policy. In 1984, final support was provided to the Group of Thirty, a nonprofit consultative group initiated by the RF in 1978 – and officially titled "Consultative Group on International Economic and Monetary Affairs" – to deal with international economic and monetary problems.
In 1986, the decision was made to close the International Relations division of the RF, a decision based both on the need to concentrate time and resources on the RF's new directions in developing-country programs and on evidence of substantially increased contribution by other foundations to the international relations field, especially in the area of arms control. (Summary of Minutes, RF Board of Trustees Meeting, June 20, 1986) A number of the program interests of the IR division relating to international development were incorporated in the RF's new International Program to Support Science-Based Development. In all instances, grant commitments made prior to the decision to close were not affected. The IR program was formally terminated on December 31, 1986.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of this series is correspondence. Records also include minutes, evaluations, and supplementary material of a general nature about the Conflict in International Relations/International Relations program, as well as documentation of grants awarded and fellowship files. Many of the grant and fellowship files are enriched by supplementary material, which may be in the form of publications, papers, reports, agendas or minutes of conferences, books, or other printed material. The supplementary material often contains the fruit that has resulted from a grant or fellowship.
The material in this series primarily covers the period from 1972/73 - when the Conflict in International Relations program was first established - through 1986, when its successor, the International Relations program, was terminated. Earliest dated material, however, dates from 1960 and latest is from 1994.
Arrangement
Series 155 contains one subseries - Subseries 155E: International Relations - Fellowships.
The arrangement reflects the filing system used by the Foundation, with minutes, correspondence and general information placed at the beginning of the series followed by material on grantee institutions, arranged alphabetically. Files are arranged in chronological order. Within each folder, material is arranged in chronological order for the first half of the collection and in reverse chronological order for the last half of the collection.
- International Relations, 1971-1989; 155
  - Minutes, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Front of File Material, 1976-1973, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Program Reports, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1973 February-May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1973 July-November (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1974 January-July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1974 August-December (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1975 January-June (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1975 July-December (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1976 January-April (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1976 June-December (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1977 January-June (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1977 July-December (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1978 January-April (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1978 May-July (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1978 August-September (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1978 October-December (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1979 January-August (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1979 September-December (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1981 January-April (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1981 May-December (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1981 January-March (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1982 April-December (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1984 January-August (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1984 September-December (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 34A)
  - Evaluations (I): List of International Relations Grants and Evaluations, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Evaluations (II): Appropriations (I), 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Evaluations (III): Appropriations (II), 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Evaluations (IV): Appropriations (III), 1977-1979 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Evaluations (V): Appropriations (IV), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Evaluations (VI): Appropriations (V), 1981-1985 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Evaluations (VII): SIE/ID Grants-in-Aid, Appropriations, 1974-1985 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Evaluations (VIII): Grants-in-Aid (I), 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Evaluations (IX): Grants-in-Aid (II), 1975 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Evaluations (X): Grants-in-Aid (III), 1976 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Evaluations (XI): Grants-in-Aid (IV), 1977 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Evaluations (XII): Grants-in-Aid (V), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Evaluations (XIII): Grants-in-Aid (VI), 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Evaluations (XIV): Grants-in-Aid (VII), 1981 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Evaluations (XV): Grants-in-Aid (VIII), 1982 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Evaluations (XVI): Grants-in-Aid (IX), 1983 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Evaluations (XVII): Grants-in-Aid (X), 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Evaluations (XVIII): Fellowships (I), 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Evaluations (XIX): Fellowships (II), 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Evaluations (XX): Fellowships (III), 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Evaluations (XXI): Allocations and Fellowships 101-157, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Supplementary Material (I), 1974 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Supplementary Material (II), 1976 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Supplementary Material (III): "Proposed International Relations Program", Presented at Trustee Meeting, April 6, 1977, 1977 April 6 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Supplementary Material (IV), 1977, 1979-1980 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Supplementary Material (V): "Report to the Rockefeller Foundation Trustees on Redesign of the International Relations Program", 1981 November 19 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Supplementary Material (VI), 1981 November 19 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Supplementary Material (VII), 1981 November 19 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Supplementary Material (VIII), 1981 November 19 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Supplementary Material (IX), 1981 November 19 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Supplementary Material (X), 1981 November 19 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Supplementary Material (XI), 1981 November (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Supplementary Material (XII): "A Survey of United States Institutions Engaged in International Relations Research and Related Activities: A Preliminary Report", Edwin A. Deagle, Jr., 1981 December 1 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Supplementary Material (XIII), 1983 March (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Supplementary Material (XIV): "International Relations Research: Emerging Trends Outside the United States, 1981-1982", Edited by John Stremlau, 1983 November (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Supplementary Material (XV), 1985 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Supplementary Material (XVI): Fellowship Program, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Staff Position, 1975 December-1976 January (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Staff Position, 1976 February (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Staff Position, 1976 March-June (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Andronico Oduogo Adede, 1981, 1983-1985 (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - (489) - Advice Centres Association: Coordinator, 1986 May (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - (489) - Advice Centres Association: Coordinator, 1986 August-1987 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - (489) - Advice Centres Association: Coordinator, 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 78)
  - Aesculapius International Medicine: Uruguay Medical Conference, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 79)
  - Aesculapius International Medicine: Uruguay Medical Conference, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 79A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from scholarly access - Personnel material.
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1979-1980 February (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1980 March-April (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1980 May (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1980 June-December (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1981 January-May (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1981 June-December (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1982 January (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - African Economic Cooperation, 1982 February-October (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - African Economic Cooperation: Supplementary Material (I), 1979-1980, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - African Economic Cooperation: Supplementary Material (II), 1980, no date (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - African Economic Cooperation: Supplementary Material (III), 1980 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - African Economic Cooperation: Supplementary Material (IV), 1980 (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - African Economic Cooperation: Supplementary Material (V), 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - African Economic Cooperation: Supplementary Material (VI), 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - African Economic Cooperation: Supplementary Material (VII), 1982 (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - (489) - African Writers' Association: Maropodi Mapalakanye, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - (489) - African Writers' Association: Maropodi Mapalakanye, 1986-1989 (Box 10, Folder 96)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report, 1982 January (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report, 1982 February-July (Box 10, Folder 98)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report, 1982 August-December (Box 10, Folder 99)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 100)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report, 1984, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (I), 1982 March-May (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (II), 1982 June (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (III), 1982 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (IV), 1982 August-September (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (V), 1982 September-October (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (VI), 1982 September-October (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (VII), 1982 October (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: European Security Report: Supplementary Material (VIII), 1982 November-1983 (Box 11, Folder 109)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: U. S.-Soviet Weapons in Space, 1984 January-May (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences: U. S.-Soviet Weapons in Space, 1984 July-1987, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - American Assembly: China Conference, 1980-1982, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - American Assembly: Mexican-American Relations, 1979-1982 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - American Assembly: U. S.-Canada Relations, 1983-1986 (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - American Assembly: U. S.-Canada Relations, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: Journals for Poland, 1982-1985 (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: Polish Scholars, 1981-1983 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges, 1980 February-November (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges, 1980 December-1981 August (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges, 1981 September-1984 (Box 12, Folder 120)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (I), 1975, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (II), 1976, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (III), 1979 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (IV), 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (V), 1979-1981 (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (VI), 1982 (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (VII), 1982 (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (VIII): International Research & Exchanges Board (IREX) Occasional Papers, Vol. l, No. 1, "A Balance Sheet for East-West Exchanges", 1980 (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (IX): International Research & Exchanges Board (IREX) Occasional Papers, Vol. 1, No. 2, "Economic Management and Mismanagement", Vol. 1, No. 3, "Ethnicity and Nationalism", 1980 (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (X): International Research & Exchanges Board (IREX) Occasional Papers, Vol. 1, No. 4, "Patterns of Daily Life", Vol. 1, No. 5, "Historical Continuity and Change", 1980 (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-East European Exchanges: Supplementary Material (XI): International Research & Exchanges Board (IREX) Occasional Papers, Vol. 3, No. 1, "Union-Management Relations and Worker Appeal Procedures in Poland", Vol. 5, No. 2, "Assimilation and Retention of Ethnic Identity in Uzbekistan", 1980 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - American Council of Learned Societies: U. S.-Soviet Planning Meeting, 1983-1984 (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - American Enterprise Institute: Middle East and the U. S., 1983 August (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - American Enterprise Institute: Middle East and the U. S., 1983 December (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - American Enterprise Institute: Middle East and the U. S., 1984-1988 (Box 13, Folder 135)
  - American Law Institute: Foreign Relations Law, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - American Law Institute: Foreign Relations Law, 1978-1979, 1981-1982, 1985, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - American Law Institute: Foreign Relations Law: Evaluation, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - American Society of International Law: Trade Relations, 1982 January (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - American Society of International Law: Trade Relations, 1982 December (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - American Society of International Law: Trade Relations, 1983-1985 (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - American Society of International Law: Trade Relations, 1986-1987 (Box 13, Folder 142)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food, 1976-1977 March (Box 13, Folder 143)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food, 1977 April-August (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food, 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 146)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food: Evaluation, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 147)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food: Supplementary Material (I): Conference Papers (I), 1978 April (Box 14, Folder 148)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food: Supplementary Material (II): Conference Papers (II), 1978 April (Box 14, Folder 149)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food: Supplementary Material (III), 1978 April (Box 14, Folder 150)
  - American Universities Field Staff: Politics of Food: Supplementary Material, 1979 (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - (489) – Archdiocese of Pretoria: Transvaal Rural Aid and Development Program, 1985-1986 May (Box 14, Folder 152)
  - (489) – Archdiocese of Pretoria: Transvaal Rural Aid and Development Program, 1986 June-1987, 1989-1991 (Box 14, Folder 153)
  - (489) – Archdiocese of Pretoria: Transvaal Rural Aid and Development Program: Supplementary Material (I), 1985 October (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - (489) – Archdiocese of Pretoria: Transvaal Rural Aid and Development Program: Supplementary Material (II), 1985 December (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - Asia Society: China Council and Asia: Front of File Material, 1980, 1983-1984, 1986-1987 (Box 14, Folder 156)
  - Asia Society: China Council and Asia, 1980-1981 (Box 14, Folder 157)
  - Asia Society: China Council and Asia, 1982 (Box 14, Folder 158)
  - Asia Society: China Council and Asia, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 159)
  - Asia Society: China Council and Asia, 1984 January-May (Box 15, Folder 160)